Personal papers of Desmond McCarthy
World Bank Group Archives
Personal papers of Desmond McCarthy
1964, 1976 - 2006
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_112
7.47 linear feet of textual files
World Bank Group Archives
McCarthy, Desmond
Desmond McCarthy was born in Cork, Ireland on December 2, 1936. He received a B.E. Electrical Engineering from National University of Ireland in 1958, followed by a PhD in Electrical Engineering from New York University in 1966 and an M.S. Economics from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1975. He subsequently spent time as a researcher at MIT prior to joining the World Bank.
McCarthy joined the World Bank in June 1981. During his 18 years as a staff member and ten more as a consultant, McCarthy held various positions in the operational, policy, research, and evaluation units of the Bank.
In 1981 McCarthy was an Economist in the Comparative Analysis and Projections Division of the Economic Analysis and Projects Department (EPDCA). The EPD was located in the Development Policy Vice Presidency (VPD), the Bank's research arm; it was transferred, along with most VPD functions, into the new Economics Research Staff (ERS) Vice Presidency in 1982. The EPD was primarily responsible for reviewing the Regional Vice Presidency's country economic analyses and programs and developing and operating macro-economic data systems related to national accounts, debt, capital flows, and trade.
In 1983 McCarthy joined the Country Policy Department (CPD). CPD was located in the Bank's Operations Policy Vice Presidency (OP), although it had previously been located in the Development Policy Vice Presidency (VPD). CPD focused on country policy and strategy and was primarily responsible for improving country and economic sector work in Bank lending operations.
In 1985 McCarthy entered the Bank's operations complex for the first time when he joined the Latin America and the Caribbean Vice Presidency (LCN) as a Senior Economist in the River Plate and Bolivia Division (LC2PB). He soon after moved into the Argentina Division (LC2AR) where he was the country economist for Argentina. Following the Bank-wide 1987 reorganization, McCarthy remained a Senior Economist in LCN but moved into the Country Operations Division of the Country Department responsible Costa Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, Mexico, Nicaragua, and Panama (LC2CO).
In 1988 McCarthy returned from the operations complex to the research arm of the Bank, called the Development Economics Vice Presidency after 1987. He would remain there until his retirement. His first position upon his return was in the newly established International Economics Department (IEC); the IEC had been created in the 1987 reorganization and had assumed some of the functions of the EPD. McCarthy was located in the International Economic Analysis and Prospects Division (IECAP) where he soon gained the title of Principal Research Economist.
In 1992 McCarthy moved into the new Development Policy Group (DPG) as an Economic Adviser. The DPG had previously reported to the Senior Vice President of Operations (OPNSV) in the form of the Economics Advisory Staff; it had advised the office on matters related to Country Strategy Papers (CSPs) and adjustment loans. Upon the termination of the OPNSV in 1991, it was placed in the DECVP but maintained its prior responsibilities.
Between 1993 and 1999 McCarthy served as Economic Adviser first to the DECVP and then to the Development Research Group (DECRG).
McCarthy retired from the Bank in 1999 but served as a consultant for the Bank in a variety of capacities over the subsequent decade. Units in which he served include: DECVP; the Office of Operations Evaluation (OED); the Operations Policy and Strategy Vice Presidency (OPS); the Health, Nutrition, and Population Team in the Human Development Network (HDNHE); and the Quality Assurance Group (QAG). McCarthy's last consultancy with the World Bank ended in 2010.
Published
Fonds consists of chronological files compiled by McCarthy that cover nearly his entire career at the World Bank. Fonds also contains reports and articles authored by McCarthy in both draft and published form as well as records related to his attendance and participation in a number of conferences and working groups. Records related to his work for the Quality Assurance Group (QAG) in 2004 and 2005 are also included.
Donated to the World Bank Group Archives by Desmond McCarthy in 2011.
Accruals are not expected.
Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
- Chronological files, 1983 - 1998; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_112-01; 3.32 linear feet of textual records
  Published
  Series includes Desmond McCarthy's chronological files covering nearly his entire career at the World Bank, beginning just prior to his transfer from the Comparative Analysis and Projections Division of the Economic Analysis and Projects Department (EPDCA) in 1983 to his time as Economic Adviser in the Development Economics Vice Presidency (DECVP) in 1998. Records generally consist of correspondence and memoranda between McCarthy and World Bank colleagues. Correspondence between McCarthy and individuals and institutions external to the Bank are included in lesser number. A significant amount of correspondence relates to the exchange of articles and reports for information, research, and review purposes; as such, articles and reports in final or draft form often accompany correspondence. Terms of Reference and back-to-office reports relating to mission travel by McCarthy and colleagues are included, as is correspondence related to work programs and research projects.
  Records created during McCarthy's time as an Economist in the Latin America and the Caribbean Vice Presidency (LCN) between 1985 and 1988 are plentiful and primarily relate to his work as country economist for Argentina. Records relate to McCarthy's authorship or review of Argentina's Country Program Paper (CPP) and Country Economic Memorandum (CEM) and related discussion and research on macro-economic issues including: trade, financial sector reform, public sector expenditure, economic recovery and growth, and debt management. Records also relate to a variety of new initiatives in Argentina including a Cofinancing Task Force, debt equity swaps, and a significant refinancing package. Records also include periodic economic updates on Argentina.
  Records relating to McCarthy's time in the International Economic Analysis and Prospects Division (IECAP) of the International Economics Department (IEC) between 1988 and 1992 include research on and discussion of a variety of topics including: World Bank-International Monetary Fund (IMF) relationship; impacts of the 1990 Middle East crisis on development; global economic outlooks; global capital shortages; and the environment and the world economy.
  Records relating to McCarthy's work as an Economic Adviser in the Development Policy Group (DPG) between 1992 and 1993 primarily relate to his contribution to and review of Country Strategy Papers (CSPs). Substantial records relating to CSPs for Kenya, Columbia, Chili, Bulgaria, Poland, and Indonesia are included in this series. Comments by McCarthy on drafts of CSPs for other countries are also included. Records relating to McCarthy's participation in Paris Club Meetings are also included.
  Records relating to McCarthy's time as Economic Adviser to the Chief Economist and Development Economist Vice President (DECVP) between 1993 and 1999 primarily relate to his research efforts. Topics include: public sector expenditure; impacts of environment on trade and development economics; and guidance and review of Country Assistance Strategy papers (CAS). Briefs on a variety of topics and countries for senior DECVP staff (including Chief Economists Michael Bruno [1993-1996] and Joseph Stiglitz [1997-2000]) are also included.
  Original order of records has been maintained. Note that McCarthy did not begin new folders upon transfer to new positions in different units. This results in records relating to different functions existing in the same folder.
  * See Records of the Office of the Chief Economist ([WB IBRD/IDA DEC](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-office-of-chief-economist) for records related to the research function of the World Bank.
  * See Records of the Latin America and Caribbean Regional Vice Presidency ([WB IBRD/IDA LAC](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-latin-america-and-caribbean-regional-vice-presidency)).
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 1992, 1992-01-01 - ?; 30295960
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 7/12/1993, 1993-07-12 - ?; 30295962
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 1996, 1996-01-01 - ?; 30295965
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research files - 1989, 1989-01-01 - ?; 30295957
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - 1985, 1985-01-01 - ?; 30295953
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - 1987, 1987-01-01 - ?; 30295955
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research files - 1991, 1991-01-01 - ?; 30295959
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - November - 1983 - December 1984, 1983-11-01 - ?; 30295952
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - 1986, 1986-01-01 - ?; 30295954
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research files - 1990, 1990-01-01 - ?; 30295958
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 1-6-93, 1993-01-16 - ?; 30295961
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological - Research projects - 1994, 1994-01-01 - ?; 30295963
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 1995, 1995-01-01 - ?; 30295964
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research projects - 1997, 1997-01-01 - ?; 30295966
  - Desmond McCarthy - Chronological files - Research files - 1988, 1988-01-01 - ?; 30295956
- Speeches, articles, and conference attendance and participation, 1976 - 2006; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_112-02; 2.49 linear feet of textual records
  Series contains reports and articles authored by McCarthy in both published and draft form. Published materials are usually contained in publications or as published reports. Articles and reports date from throughout McCarthy's employment at the World Bank, including his time as a consultant after his 1999 retirement. A small number of articles contained in this series were published while McCarthy was affiliated with the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in the late 1970s. Topics of the articlesare wide-ranging, but generally relate to country economic profiles, consumer behavior in developing countries, and the agriculture and nutrition sectors.
  Series also includes a number of reports published by the World Bank and authored by World Bank staff and consultants other than McCarthy. A small number of development-related speeches authored by individuals external to the World Bank are also included.
  Records related to seminar attendance and participation by McCarthy are included in this series.Records include text and slides from presentations by both McCarthy and others. The most common topic of articles, reports, and conference materials is the environment and its effect on and role in development economics. Other topics include structural adjustment and country economic profiles.
  Original order of records has been maintained.
  * See Records of the Agriculture and Rural Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA AGR](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-agriculture-and-rural-development-sector)).
  * See Records of the Population, Health, and Nutrition Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_89](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-population-health-and-nutrition-sector)).
  * See Records of the Environment Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA ENV](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-environment-sector)).
  * See Records of the Office of External Relations - Speech reference collection ([WB IBRD/IDA EXT-01](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-office-of-external-relations)) for other speeches by Bank staff.
  * See the [Documents & Reports](http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/home) for World Bank reportsauthored by Desmond McCarthy.
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on the Disclosure of Information.
  - Philippines - External Shocks and Policy Response - (draft) - 1993, 1993-01-01 - ?; 30295948
  - The Fiscal Rationale for Adjustment Lending - Draft - Anandarup Ray, 1995-05-04; 30295886
  - Ireland's Economic Recovery - A preliminary Review of the Evidence by Patrick T. Geary - Discussion - Desmond McCarthy, 30295888
  - Peer Review Comments on Several McCarthy papers, 1981-10-17 - 1993-07-29; 30295890
  - DEC - Public expenditure review - country files, 1990-04-07 - 1995-01-31; 30295901
  - Ireland's Economy in the 1980s - Stagnation and Recovery - A Comment - Number. 3 - Volume 23 - April 1992, 1992-04-01 - ?; 30295927
  - Economywide politics and the environment - Lessons from experience, 1995-01-01 - 1995-01-31; 30295906
  - Organisation for Economic co-operation and development - Economic Policy Committee Working Party Number 1 Back to Office Report - April 27 - 1992, 1992-04-27 - ?; 30295889
  - Back to office report - Fiscal Policy Reforms in Least Developed Countries - Geneva - March 16-17 - 1995, 1995-03-17 - ?; 30295883
  - Economic Stocks and Global Environment - A research Proposal, 1992-09-21; 30295876
  - Is there a Capital Shortage - F. Desmond McCarthy, 1993-12-01 - 1994-01-03; 30295873
  - Sustainable development concepts - An economic analysis, 1992-11-01 - 1992-11-30; 30295905
  - Environmental accounting for sustainable development (A UNEP - World Bank symposium), 1989-06-01 - 1989-06-30; 30295909
  - Monitoring environmental progress - March 1995 Draft, 1995-03-01 - ?; 30295907
  - Ukraine - External Shocks and Performance Responses - Ukrainian Economic Review - Volume 1 - No. 1-2 - 1995, 1995-01-01 - ?; 30295932
  - Mr. Wolfensohn's April 17 Luncheon Meeting with Dr. Stiglitz - Briefing Note, 1996-04-03; 30295887
  - Pakistan - CAS Assessment, 1996-04-04; 30295885
  - Environmental standards and international trade - Annual bank conference on Development economics, 1996-04-24 - 1996-04-26; 30295902
  - Jamaica - economic policy - development strategy and the environment - draft, 1996-05-06; 30295915
  - Phasing out leads from gasoline - World-wide experience and policy Implications, 1995-12-01 - 1996-08-31; 30295904
  - Accounting for the environment - comments by Frank Desmond McCarthy at the IUCN conference - Montreal - October 20 - 1996, 1996-10-20 - ?; 30295916
  - Draft management Responses to Operations Evaluation Report on Fiscal Management of Adjustment Lending - 1996, 1996-01-01 - ?; 30295882
  - Accounting for the future - Mark Baird - October 4 - 1995, 1995-10-04 - ?; 30295910
  - Economic Performance in Small Open Economies - The Caribbean Experience - 1980-1992 (working paper) - Internal Development Centre - November 1996, 1996-11-01 - ?; 30295931
  - United States - Russian Investment Symoposium - Harvard University - January 10 - 1997, 1997-01-10 - ?; 30295895
  - Conference on structural Adjustment and Environment - Amsterdam - February 5 - 1997, 1997-02-05 - ?; 30295899
  - Non Lending Services - Current Situation, 1994-09-21 - 1997-03-21; 30295880
  - United States - Russia Business Council - United States - Russian Trade Investment: Forecast 97 - April 1997, 1997-04-01 - ?; 30295896
  - Conference on structural adjustment and environment - Amsterdam - February 5 - 1997, 1997-02-05 - ?; 30295918
  - Luncheon Meeting with Ford Motor Company - May 23 - 1997, 1997-05-23 - ?; 30295879
  - Post Conflict Reconstruction Policy paper - Executive Summary Draft - 1996, 1996-01-01 - ?; 30295878
  - Harvard Courses - Follow up to Back to office report, 1997-07-23; 30295884
  - Private Sector Development - Group Meeting - August 29 - 1997 - Facilitating Private Involvement in Infrastructure - An Action Plan, 1997-08-29 - ?; 30295897
  - Joseph Stiglitz Speeches - The future of China and building, 1997-09-17 - 1997-09-22; 30295917
  - Seminar: Urban environment - Management Strategies - Action plans and metropolitian challenges - March 2-4 - 1998, 1998-03-02 - ?; 30295900
  - Health Consequences of Environmental Pollution - Research Paper - 1998-1999, 1998-01-01 - ?; 30295942
  - Is Growth Good for Health - Research Paper - 1999, 1999-01-01 - ?; 30295943
  - The Role of Information Technology in Attracting Foreign Investment - Creating Industrialized Zones and Developing Human Resources - World Bank Competitive Cities Congress - Case Study - Dublin - Ireland - Washington, D.C., May 19-21, 1999, 1999-05-19 - ?; 30295949
  - Research Proposals - Work Program - 1997, 1997-01-01 - ?; 30295872
  - Malaria - Research Paper - 1999, 1999-01-01 - ?; 30295944
  - The growth Cost of Malaria (working paper 7541) - National Bureau of Economic Research, INC (NBER), February 2000, 2000-02-01 - ?; 30295930
  - Restructuring fiscal management in the Kingdom of Bahrain, 2004-01-01 - 2004-01-31; 30295913
  - Bulgaria - Survey on rural development needs, 2004-04-01 - 2004-04-30; 30295908
  - MNA Region - Interim PESW Guidelines, 2004-02-01 - 2004-05-28; 30295898
  - Talking points for Mr. Nankani - Organisation for Economic co-operation and Development -Development Assistance Committee - High level Consultation on the United Nations Millennium Project - July 8 - 2004, 2004-07-08 - ?; 30295891
  - Conditionality and enhancement partnerships for reform - Gobind Nankani - Concluding remarks, 2004-06-22 - 2004-07-14; 30295914
  - Meeting of Faith and Development Leaders - Dublin - Ireland January 31 -2005 - Ireland - Economic - Structural and Institutional Change, 2005-01-31 - ?; 30295892
  - Pakistan - North West Frontier Province - Community Infrastructure Project, 2004-04-29; 30295874
  - Mr. Desmond McCarthy - Ghana - P091009 - December 6 - 2005, 2005-12-06 - ?; 30295870
  - Draft Low Income counrty under stress - Review - March 9 - 2003, 2003-03-09 - ?; 30295877
  - Global and Regional Analytical and advisory assistance - Special Administration Region - P093145 - Poverty and Inequality, 2004-08-11 - 2006-04-27; 30295871
  - The Political Economy Reform in Europe, 2006, 2006-01-01 - ?; 30295945
  - Aid Transfer and Possible Welfare Losses they may Induce - Center for International studies - MIT, 2014-08-08; 30295925
  - Economic shocks and the global environment - responses to shocks, 1992-03-01 - 1992-03-31; 30295912
  - Towards environmentally sustainable development in West Central Africa, 2014-08-08; 30295903
  - A Social Accounting Matrix for Egypt - North Holland Publishing Company - 1976, 1976-01-01 - ?; 30295929
  - How Wide is the Calorie Gap - MIT International Nutrition Planning Program - discussions papers Number 14) - 1978, 1978-01-01 - ?; 30295919
  - Multi-sector General Equilibrium Models for Egypt (working paper number 233) - MIT Department of Economics - March 1979, 1979-03-01 - ?; 30295923
  - The Katilu Irrigation Scheme in Turkana District - Kenya - A Socio-Economic Nutrition Analysis Report of a Survey - March 1979, 1979-03-01 - ?; 30295935
  - Macro Food policy planning: A General Equilibrium Model for Pakistan - The Review of Economics and Statistics - Volume LXII - Number 1 -February 1980, 1980-02-01 - ?; 30295934
  - Production - The Production module of the Brazilian General Equilibrium Model - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis - Austria - February 1981, 1981-02-01 - ?; 30295921
  - The Welfare Costs of Tied Food Aid - Methodology for Manpower Planning in Egypt - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis - Austria - February 1981, 1981-02-01 - ?; 30295922
  - Quality Effects in Consumer Behavior - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis - March 1981, 1981-03-01 - ?; 30295920
  - Flexible Dynamic Macro Level with Consistency Check - (draft), August 1981, 1981-01-01 - ?; 30295946
  - Brazil - Social Accounting Structure - (draft) - 1975, 1975-01-01 - ?; 30295947
  - Quality Effects in Consumer Behavior - The Pakistan Development Review - Volume 20 - Number 2 - 1981, 1981-01-01 - ?; 30295928
  - Kenyan Agriculture - Toward 2000 - May 1982, 1982-05-01 - ?; 30295926
  - Trade Patterns in Developing Countries - 1964-1982 - North Holland Journal of Development Economics number 27- (5-39), 1987, 1964-01-01 - ?; 30295936
  - Adjustment Policies in Developing Countries - 1978-1981, 1978-01-01 - ?; 30295881
  - Panama - Macro Economic Analysis - (draft) - 1994, 1994-01-01 - ?; 30295937
  - Malaysia - Endowment - Growth and Development - 1985, 1985-01-01 - ?; 30295940
  - Sources of Growth in Colombia 1963-1980 - Journal of Economic Studies - Volume 12 - Number 4 - 1985, 1985-01-01 - ?; 30295924
  - Argentina - Issues Paper for Economic Mission - April 1986 - Back to office report - January 28 - 1986, 1986-01-28 - ?; 30295893
  - Argentina - Economic Recovery and Growth - Escape from Hyperinflation, 1986-12-15; 30295875
  - Argentina - Towards the year 2000 - Internal Discussion Paper - 1987, 1987-01-01 - ?; 30295941
  - Argentina - Problems for Achieving Macro Stability - 1987, 1987-01-01 - ?; 30295950
  - Seminar for Latin American Economic Journalist - Buenos Aires - 1987, 1987-01-01 - ?; 30295894
  - Argentina - Economic Recovery and Growth (includes background papers 1, 2, 3, 4) - A World Bank Country Study - 1987, 1987-01-01 - ?; 30295951
  - Global Accounting Framework - 1988, 1988-01-01 - ?; 30295938
  - Padroes de Crescimento dos Paises em Desenvolvimento na Decada de 80 - President Planning Economic - Rio de Janeiro - 19(2) 309-346 - 1989, 1989-01-01 - ?; 30295933
  - Malaysia - The Global Environment (draft) - 1990, 1990-01-01 - ?; 30295939
  - Adjustments in New Zealand - External shocks and policy responses - February 1991, 1991-02-01 - ?; 30295911
  - Iceland - Pension Reform - Policy Consideration - September 1997, 1997-09-24 - ?; 30295860
- Quality Assurance Group (QAG) review and assessment, 1997 - 2005; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_112-03; 1.63 linear feet of textual records
  Series relates to work Desmond McCarthy undertook as a consultant for the Quality Assurance Group (QAG) in 2004 and 2005.
  Series includes records relating to a quality assessment of Non-Lending Technical Assistance (NLTA) conducted by the Quality Assurance Group (QAG) on which McCarthy served as a panelist in 2004. Records relating to assessments of the State Owned Bank Technical Assistance project in Romania and the Services Sector Census project in China are included. Records include background information on each project and QAG guidelines for the assessment process.
  Records related to the QAG assessment of the Customs Modernization Handbook are also included in this series. The Handbook was intended to provide guidance to organizations and individuals involved in the preparation and implementation of customs modernization projects. Records include a copy of the handbook itself as well as comments on the Handbook and records related to the release and dissemination of the Handbook.
  Series also includes records related to a 2003-2004 QAG review of analytical and advisory activities (AAA) primarily related to Bulgaria, including reviews of: public expenditure issues; rural development sector; Country Procurement Assessment Report (CPAR); and a national energy efficiency study. Records consist of background materials and guidance questionnaires: the latter often contain hand-written notes presumably made by McCarthy.
  * See Records of the Office of Operations Policy ([WB IBRD/IDA OP](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-office-of-operations-policy) for records related to the Quality Assurance Group.